Fausold, Martin; Papers ua902.078
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Martin Fausold Papers
1919, 1945-2008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua902.078
10.39 cubic ft. 1 Digital Files
The Martin Fausold Papers documents Fausold's involvement in in the Faculty Association of the State University of New York and his two-decade long Oral History of SUNY Project.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of several folders marked below. While Fausold subsequently asked individuals interviewed for the Oral History of SUNY Project to sign a clearance form, not all interview files donated to the archive contain forms. Therefore notes, transcripts and audio of a select number of interviews are restricted until clearance may be obtained by the archivists from the interviewees or their heirs.
Acquisition Information
Martin Fausold donated all of the materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2008.
Biographical Sketch
Born in Pennsylvania in 1921, Dr. Martin L. Fausold was a Distinguished Professor of History (later Emeritus) at the State University of New York (SUNY) at Geneseo, an eminent scholar of Herbert C. Hoover and author of five books and numerous articles during his lifetime. Matin Fausold received his bachelor's degree in History from Gettysburg College, served in World War II, and completed his doctoral degree in 1953 from Syracuse University, in the Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs.
Dr. Fausold was a professor at SUNY Buffalo and SUNY Cortland, and then joined the faculty at SUNY Geneseo in 1958 as chair of the Division of Social Science. Dr. Fausold also was Vice President and later President of the Faculty Association of the State University of New York (currently the SUNY Faculty Senate). SUNY honored him with the rank of Distinguished Service Professor in 1985. He retired from teaching in 1992.
Beginning in 1988, Dr. Fausold began a 20-year effort to create an oral history of the SUNY System that was still ongoing at the time of his death. This project involved significant research and interviewing of key SUNY administrators, board members and faculty and New York State budget directors, and comprises the majority of this collection. Based upon his interests, Dr. Fausold helped develop and coordinate the first SUNY history conference in 1991, held at SUNY Brockport, and was actively engaged in planning for a conference honoring the 60th anniversary of SUNY, which was subsequently held in late 2008.
Dr. Fausold passed away in October 2008, preceded in death by his wife Daryl Clement Fausold.
Scope and Contents
The Martin Fausold Papers document his work with the State University of New York System, including his 20-year long Oral History of SUNY Project, which attempted to record the history of the SUNY System through interviews with key administrators, historians and faculty, and his involvement with the Faculty Association of the State University of New York. This collection is divided into four series arranged alphabetically: The Oral History of SUNY Project, Research and Subject Files, Faculty Association of the State University of New York (FASUNY), and the 1991 Brockport Conference.
The Oral History of SUNY Project series contains audio cassette tapes, transcripts, notes and related correspondence of the interviews conducted by Fausold and his colleagues. His research materials for the Oral History of SUNY Project as well as other subject files are housed in the Research and Subject Files. Fausold's FASUNY records, which include newsletters, meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports are retained in their own respective series. Lastly, the 1991 Brockport Conference, the first conference devoted to the history of the SUNY System, is separated into its own series. It includes the Conference's program, lists of participants, and the papers presented.
Researchers should note that many materials from the Oral History of SUNY Project related to SUNY Geneseo are housed at SUNY Geneseo, where Fausold served as a Distinguished Professor of History. In addition, as the Fausold Papers at the University at Albany contain only a limited number of personal papers, researchers should instead contact SUNY Geneseo or Indiana University of Pennsylvania, which holds the broader Fausold Family Papers, for more information.
Please also note that the family of Samuel Gould, chancellor of SUNY from 1964-1970 and interviewed for Fausold's Oral History of SUNY Project in 1989, later gave Fausold materials created and amassed by the former chancellor. Since the materials were more of a personal nature and are not directly related to the Oral History of SUNY Project, archivists are adding them to the Samuel Gould Papers (APAP-058) already housed in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Researchers may consult other SUNY and educational collections and records held in the M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, which, in addition to the the papers of Chancellor Gould, includes the papers of Assistant to the Chancellor John Mather, SUNY Trustee Chairmen or chairs Frank Moore and Donald Blinken, as well as many other retained records relating to SUNY Central.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred four monographs: The Basic School written by Ernest L. Boyer, Ernest L. Boyer Selected Speeches 1979-1995 edited by Lauren Maidment Green, The Executive Budget in New York State and Higher Education in Crisis edited by William C. Barba to the book division of Special Collections. These will be catalogued and included at a later date in the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - The Oral History of SUNY Project, 1988-2006, Undated
Series 2 - General Research and Subject Files, 1919-2008, Undated
Series 3 - FASUNY, 1948-1969, Undated
Series 4 - 1991 Brockport Conference, 1982, 1989-1991, Undated
All series are arranged alphabetically.
State University of New York SUNY, Central Administration; Education; Oral history--New York (State); Education--New York (State)--History; State colleges and universities--United States; Albany (N.Y.); Brockport (N.Y.); Geneseo (N.Y.); New York (State); Interviews; Transcripts; Newsletters; Articles; Dissertations; Minutes; Audio cassettes; Digital Files; UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Fausold, Martin L., 1921-; State University of New York; State University of New York. University Faculty Senate
- The Oral History of SUNY Project, 1988-2006; Undated; 1; 3.2 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The first series in the Fausold Collection consists of interviews conducted by Fausold for the Oral History of SUNY project from 1988 to 1997. Fausold's colleague Wayne Mahood, a Distinguished Professor of Education at SUNY Geneseo, helped conduct some of the interviews as did others. The archivist noted interviews not conducted by Fausold in the inventory below as well as the titles held by the interviewees in the SUNY System or within New York State government. This series includes both the recorded interviews on audio cassettes as well as paper transcripts. A small number of interviews, however, are not transcribed. A majority of the interviews transcribed feature multiple versions, as both Fausold and the interviewee edited them. Interview files typically contain interview transcriptions, a clearance form signed by the interviewee, and background information. Fausold kept lists of interviewees, potential interviewees, and the status of each interview.
  - Annotated Bibliography of Primary and Secondary Sources for Project, Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 1)
  - Clearance Forms, 1989-2006 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 2)
  - Clearance Forms in Agreement with Columbia University, 1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 3)
  - Clearance Needed List, Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence about History Senior Seminar Oral History Interview Project, 1989 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence about Oral History Project, 1993-2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence about Reviewed Transcripts with K. Mackenzie, 2002 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 7)
  - Handwritten Notes for Interview Secondary Sources, Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 8)
  - History of SUNY Project Budget Estimate, Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 9)
  - Index Card Notes about Interviewees, Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 10)
  - Interview with Albert J. Abrams [Former Employee of New York State Senate, Elected Secretary of the Senate], [RESTRICTED], 1989 February 06 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 11)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Interview with Albert J. Abrams [Former Employee of New York State Senate, Elected Secretary of the Senate], [RESTRICTED], 1989 February 06 (Cassette 1-2)
  - Interview with Abbott, [RESTRICTED], Undated (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 12)
  - Interview with Donald Axelrod [Former Assistant State Budget Director and Professor Emeritus and Former Chairman of the Department of Public Administration and Policy at SUNY Albany], 1993 April 04 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 13-14)
  - Interview with Donald Axelrod [Former Assistant State Budget Director and Professor Emeritus and Former Chairman of the Department of Public Administration and Policy at SUNY Albany], 1993 April 04 (Cassette 3-4)
  - Interview with Murray Block [Former Deputy to the Chancellor with Responsibility for Community Colleges, also Served as Interim President of Orange County Community College, Broome Community College and Columbia-Green Community College], 1989 April 05 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 15)
  - Interview with Francis Bonner [Professor of Chemistry, SUNY Stony Brook], 1989 May 03 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 16)
  - Interview with Francis Bonner [Professor of Chemistry, SUNY Stony Brook], 1989 May 03 (Cassette 5-6)
  - Interview with Albert Brown [Former President of SUNY Brockport], 1989 February 13 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 17)
  - Interview with Albert Brown [Former President of SUNY Brockport], 1989 February 13 (Cassette 7-8)
  - Interview with Joseph Burke [Former President, SUNY Plattsburgh and Provost, SUNY], [RESTRICTED], 1997 June 16 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 18)
  - Interview with John Burton [Former New York State Director of the Budget], 1989 August 08 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 19)
  - Interview with John Burton [Former New York State Director of the Budget], 1989 August 08 (Cassette 9-12)
  - Interview with William Carlson [Former President, SUNY], 1989 February 23 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 20-21)
  - Interview with William Carlson [Former President, SUNY], 1989 February 23 (Cassette 13-15)
  - Interview with Thomas Colahan [Former Vice President of Academic Affiars, SUNY Geneseo], 1997 April 15 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 22-23)
  - Interview with William J. Cotton [Former Director, Division of Education, SUNY Geneseo] (Interview Conducted by Laura Freedell), 1989 December 10 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 24)
  - Interview with Charles H. Foster [Former Vice President for Business Affairs, SUNY Geneseo] (Interview conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1988 August 12 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 25-26)
  - Interview with Charles H. Foster [Former Vice President for Business Affairs, SUNY Geneseo] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1988 August 12 (Cassette 21-24)
  - Interview with Reuben Frodin [Former Executive Dean for SUNY Four Year and Professional Colleges], 1989; 1991 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 27-28)
  - Interview with Reuben Frodin [Former Executive Dean for SUNY Four Year and Professional Colleges], 1989 (Cassette 25-26)
  - Interview with James Frost [Former Assistnat to the President and Dean, SUNY Oneonta, Executive Dean for SUNY Four Year and Professional Colleges, and Executive Dean, University Colleges], 1989 May 10 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 29-30)
  - Interview with Sanford Gordon [Former Faculty, SUNY Oneonta and Assistant Vice Chancellor for Policy and Planning, SUNY], 1989 October 04 (Box 1 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 31)
  - Interview with Sanford Gordon [Former Faculty, SUNY Oneonta and Assistant Vice Chancellor for Policy and Planning, SUNY], 1989 October 04 (Cassette 27-30)
  - Interview with Samuel Gould [Former Chancellor, SUNY], 1989 February 21-1989 February 22 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 1-3)
  - Interview with Samuel Gould [Former Chancellor, SUNY], 1989 February 21-1989 February 22 (Cassette 31-36)
  - Interview with Mort Grant [Former Research Director, SUNY], [RESTRICTED], 1989 February 02 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 4)
  - Interview with Walter Harding [Former Professor of English, SUNY Geneseo] (Interview Conducted by Ms. Baker), [RESTRICTED], 1989 November 17 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 5)
  - Interview with T. Norman Hurd [Former New York State Director of the Budget], 1989 February 07 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 6)
  - Interview with T. Norman Hurd [Former New York State Director of the Budget], 1989 February 07 (Cassette 37-38)
  - Interview with Edward Jakubauskas [Former President, SUNY Geneseo], [RESTRICTED], 1989 August 18 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 7)
  - Interview with Edward Jakubauskas [Former President, SUNY Geneseo], [RESTRICTED], 1989 August 18 (Cassette 39-40)
  - Interview with D. Bruce Johnstone [Former Chancellor, SUNY and Professor of Higher and Comparative Education, SUNY Buffalo], [RESTRICTED], 1997 December 18 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 8-10)
  - Interview with D. Bruce Johnstone [Former Chancellor, SUNY and Professor of Higher and Comparative Education, SUNY Buffalo], [RESTRICTED], 1997 December 18 (Cassette 41-44)
  - Interview with Jim Kalas [Former Associate Provost for Research and Planning, SUNY], [RESTRICTED], 1997 June 17 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 11)
  - Interview with Oscar Lanford [Former President, SUNY Fredonia and Vice Chancellor for Campus Development and Head of the University Construction Fund, SUNY], 1988 October 24 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 12-13)
  - Interview with Oscar Lanford [Former President, SUNY Fredonia and Vice Chancellor for Campus Development and Head of the University Construction Fund, SUNY], 1988 October 24 (Cassette 45-50)
  - Interview with Sanford Levine [Counsel, SUNY], 1989 April 06 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 14-15)
  - Interview with Sanford Levine [Counsel, SUNY], 1989 April 06 (Cassette 51-52)
  - Interview with Kenneth Levison [Former Vice President for Administration and Finance, SUNY Geneseo], [RESTRICTED], 1997 December 22 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 16)
  - Interview with James Lyng [Former Executive Director for Central Administration, SUNY], [RESTRICTED], 1988 October 04 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 17)
  - Interview with James Lyng [Former Executive Director for Central Administration, SUNY], [RESTRICTED], 1988 October 04 (Cassette 53-54)
  - Interview with Herbert McArthur [Former Associate Vice Chancellor, SUNY] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1988 October 26 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 18-19)
  - Interview with Herbert McArthur [Former Associate Vice Chancellor, SUNY] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1988 October 26 (Cassette 64-67)
  - Interview with Kenneth MacKenzie [Associate Vice Chancellor for Programs and Planning, SUNY], 1988 October 25 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 20)
  - Interview with Kenneth MacKenzie [Associate Vice Chancellor for Programs and Planning, SUNY], 1988 October 25 (Cassette 68-70)
  - Interview with Robert MacVittie [Former President, SUNY Geneseo] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), [RESTRICTED], 1989 June 26 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 21-22)
  - Interview with Freda Martens [Former Director of the Research Association at SUNY Albany, in Charge of Instructional Research at Dutchess County Community College and Published Scholar of and Advocate for Higher Education], [RESTRICTED], 1987 April 07 (Box 2 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 23)
  - Interview with Freda Martens [Former Director of the Research Association at SUNY Albany, in Charge of Instructional Research at Dutchess County Community College and Published Scholar of and Advocate for Higher Education], [RESTRICTED], 1987 April 07 (Cassette 55-57)
  - Interview with John J. Mather [Former Executive Assistant to the Chancellor, SUNY, Associate Chancellor for Continuing Education and Public Service, SUNY and Administrator of the SUNY System Business Development Services Office], 1989 September 01 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 1-2)
  - Interview with John J. Mather [Former Executive Assistant to the Chancellor, SUNY, Associate Chancellor for Continuing Education and Public Service, SUNY and Administrator of the SUNY System Business Development Services Office], 1989 September 01 (Cassette 58-63)
  - Interview with Beth Moore [Former Chairperson, SUNY Board of Trustees], [RESTRICTED], 1991 June 13 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 3)
  - Interview with Francis Muench [Former Dean of the College, SUNY Cortland and President, SUNY Geneseo], [RESTRICTED], 1989 May 02 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 4)
  - Interview with J. Lawrence Murray [Former Chief Administrative Officer, SUNY], 1988 October 28 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 5-6)
  - Interview with J. Lawrence Murray [Former Chief Administrative Officer, SUNY], 1988 October 28 (Cassette 71-73)
  - Interview with Paul Neureiter [Former Professor, SUNY Geneseo] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1988 March 02 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 7)
  - Interview with Thomas Peterson [Deputy to the Chancellor for Campus Liasons, SUNY], [RESTRICTED], 1988 October 03 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 8)
  - Interview with Thomas Peterson [Deputy to the Chancellor for Campus Liasons, SUNY], [RESTRICTED], 1988 October 03 (Cassette 74-75)
  - Interview with Harry Porter [Former Provost, SUNY] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1989 March 27 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 9)
  - Interview with Harry Porter [Former Provost, SUNY] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1989 March 27 (Cassette 76-79)
  - Interview with Gladys Rhodes [Former Chairperson, Department of Special Education, State University College] (Interview Conducted by Fausold, W. Mahood, and B. Mahood), 1988 April 07 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 10)
  - Interview with Bruce Ristow [Associate Provost, SUNY Geneseo], 1997 July 08 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 11-13)
  - Interview with George Shapiro [SUNY Advocate], [RESTRICTED], 1989 May 04 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 14)
  - Interview with George Shapiro [SUNY Advocate], [RESTRICTED], 1989 May 04 (Cassette 80-81)
  - Interview with Harry Spindler [Senior Vice Chancellor, SUNY], 1989 August 31 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 15-16)
  - Interview with Harry Spindler [Senior Vice Chancellor, SUNY], 1989 August 31 (Cassette 82-85)
  - Interview with Paul Veillette [New York State Chief Budget Examiner for Lower and Higher Education], 1997 October 24 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 17)
  - Interview with Paul Veillette [New York State Chief Budget Examiner for Lower and Higher Education], 1997 October 24 (Cassette 86-88)
  - Interview with James J. Warren [Former Member, Board of Trustees, SUNY], 1988 November 22 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 18-19)
  - Interview with Don J. Wickham [Former Member, Board of Trustees, SUNY] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1991 March 03 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 20-21)
  - Interview with Don J. Wickham [Former Member, Board of Trustees, SUNY] (Interview Conducted by Fausold and Mahood), 1991 March 03 (Cassette 89-91)
  - Interview with Winnie Widmer (Mrs. Francis Downey) [Former Counsel SUNY Research Foundation], [RESTRICTED], 1989 February 08 (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 22)
  - Interview with Winnie Widmer (Mrs. Francis Downey) [Former Counsel SUNY Research Foundation], [RESTRICTED], 1989 February 08 (Cassette 92-93)
  - List of Interview Transcriptions and Page Count, Undated (Box 3 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 23)
  - List of Interviewees and Materials, Undated (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 1)
  - List of Potential Interviewees, Undated (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 2)
  - List of Oral Transcriptions, Undated (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 3)
  - Manuscript Materials for the Oral History of SUNY Project at SUNY Geneseo, Undated (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 5)
  - Notes on Conversation with Loren Baritz and Letter Declining Participation, 1988-1989 (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 6)
  - Status of Audiotaped Interviews, Undated (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 7)
  - Request to Interview Henrick Dullea [Vice President for University Relations, SUNY Geneseo], 1997 November 09 (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 8)
  - Research Assignments for Oral History Project, Undated (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 9)
  - Thank You Letters to Participants, 1988-1989 (Box 4 (1-The Oral History of SUNY Project), Folder 10)
- General Research and Subject Files, 1919-2008; Undated; 2; 4 cubic ft. 1 Digital Files
  The second series of this collection consists of Fausold's research and subject files. A majority of this series are research materials for the Oral History of SUNY Project. These materials include a large number of dissertations, newspaper articles, and multiple finding aides to archival collections, some annotated by Fausold. There are also multiple copies of Fausold's Draft History of the State University of New York as well as executive committee meeting minutes and membership lists. Fausold's applications and acceptance letters into the Research Foundation and Visiting Professorships' GRI Program can be found in this series. Fausold also kept records of Research Foundation expenses, correspondence, and funding possibilities. This series also contains Fausold's correspondence from the 1980s to the 2000s about the Oral History of SUNY Project.
  - Access to Free Public Higher Education in New York City: 1847-1964 by F. Neuman, 1984 (Box 1 (2-General Research and Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Anecdotal History of SUNY, 1992; Undated (Box 1 (2-General Research and Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Archived Material Sent to Fausold from the Boyer Center, 2007 (Box 1 (2-General Research and Subject Files), Folder 3)